<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: leadership | Brandon Liu]]></title>
  <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/categories/leadership/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://branliu.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-31T22:29:30-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://branliu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Liu]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandon.k.liu@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Subtle Art of Becoming a Master of Facilitating Meetings]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2012/05/25/the-subtle-art-of-becoming-a-master-of-facilitating-meetings/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-25T18:09:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2012/05/25/the-subtle-art-of-becoming-a-master-of-facilitating-meetings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What makes someone a master of facilitating meetings?</p>

<p>When people teach others how to run effective meetings, they usually cover
specific meeting techniques that can be used. Here are some of the most
commons ones:</p>

<ul>
<li>Allow everyone a chance to speak, and actively encourage reticent
participants.</li>
<li>Use an agenda, schedule each agenda item (as opposed to just listing
them), and send it out before the meeting.</li>
<li>Create a list of action items to follow up on after the meeting, with assigned
persons of responsibility and deadlines.</li>
</ul>


<p>Implementing these techniques will undoubtedly make your meetings more
effective, but I feel that these recommendations miss the high-level skills
that are often more subtle to articulate. The actions above will help anyone
become competent at running meetings, but there is much more that is needed to
become a true master at meetings.</p>

<p>Briefly, I discuss two skills I believe are core to any outstanding
meeting facilitator. While my points may be less actionable than many of the
techniques you can find online, I believe they provide a valuable framework
for evaluating yourself as an effective leader during meetings. Self-awareness
is the first step to personal growth!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I do not take the time to expand upon each point at length here, so be sure
take the time to digest each point.</p>

<h2>Facilitation</h2>

<p>To run an outstanding meeting, you must be an outstanding facilitator of
discussion. The skills involved in being an outstanding facilitator include:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Controlling the level and detail of discussion.</strong> For example, don&rsquo;t discuss
logistics when discussing strategy and vision, and vice versa. Doing so will
waste time and the meeting will lose focus.</li>
<li><strong>Controlling the time given for a discussion.</strong> Allow ample time for discussion,
but cut it off and make a decision when needed. You cannot wait for unanimity,
and you certainly cannot make everyone happy. If a decision can’t be made,
determine concrete action items to be done before a decision can be made and
move on.</li>
<li><strong>Controlling the scope of the discussion.</strong> Take on one item at a time, come to
some sort of actionable conclusion, and then move on to the next item. Don’t
allow the discussion to stray off course. New discussion items can be added to
the bottom of the agenda.</li>
<li><strong>Breaking down what is said into its core message</strong> by repeating the essence when
needed. People can be verbose and roundabout when speaking, and it often
obscures their argument to the rest of the group, and even to themselves.
Paring their thoughts down to the essential and rephrasing them to directly
address what has been said will ensure that the discussion makes progress.</li>
<li><strong>Pointing out logical fallacies</strong> when you hear them. Ad hominem, straw mans, and
appeals to majority are especially common and undesirable. Understand proper
argumentation to ensure that your decisions are based on facts.</li>
<li><strong>Being open-minded</strong> by encouraging and incorporating feedback. Allow everyone to
share their thoughts, give each careful consideration, and push ahead with the
best ones. You don’t even have to have the majority on your side – just make
sure everyone feels that their voice was heard.</li>
<li><strong>Guiding the outcome of the meeting</strong>, rather than directing it. You need your
team to be invested in the decision-making process, so that they will be
committed to the ultimate outcome.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Knowing your desired outcome</h2>

<p>No one ever consistently accomplishes anything great without setting his or
her intentions and desired outcomes. This will also help you keep your meeting
on track and on time. Running a highly effective meeting requires:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Knowing exactly why you are having the meeting and what you want to get out of
it.</strong> You must know exactly why every single agenda item is on there. What do
you want to accomplish by the end of the meeting?</li>
<li><strong>Knowing exactly why every attendee must be there.</strong> If you value people’s time,
they will value yours.</li>
<li><strong>Never holding a meeting for the sake of holding a meeting.</strong> This will be the
death of your team&rsquo;s morale and productivity. If you have a weekly meeting
planned, but there isn’t much to discuss, just cancel the meeting!</li>
</ol>


<p>Running an effective meeting is a subtle and nuanced art requiring a high
level of social awareness and focus throughout the discussion. In my opinion,
mastery of these skills is very difficult and few people have attained it. If
you want to improve yourself, pay close attention during discussions and try
to get a high-level feel for the direction, scope, and level of the discussion
without getting bogged down in what is actually being said. Develop an
intuition for guiding and facilitating discussion by leading meetings and then
self-reflecting afterward.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
