<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: development | Brandon Liu]]></title>
  <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/categories/development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://branliu.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-29T14:34:13-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://branliu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Liu]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandon.k.liu@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Latest Findings on Unconditional Cash Transfers: GiveDirectly]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2013/10/25/latest-findings-on-unconditional-cash-transfers/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T10:59:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2013/10/25/latest-findings-on-unconditional-cash-transfers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A policy brief on the NGO <a href="http://www.givedirectly.org/" title="GiveDirectly">GiveDirectly</a> was just <a href="http://web.mit.edu/joha/www/publications/Haushofer_Shapiro_Policy_Brief_UCT_2013.10.22.pdf" title="GiveDirectly Policy Brief">released</a> today.
GiveDirectly is an NGO founded by two MIT Economics PhD students to provide
unconditional cash transfers (UCTs) to poor households in Kenya, in which they
give large lump sums of money (up to two years worth of income) with no
strings attached. Unconditional cash transfers have become one of the most
exciting opportunities and areas of research in development economics over the
past few years. GiveDirectly, one of the foremost UCT programs in the field,
has received <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/08/18/magazine/is-it-nuts-to-give-to-the-poor-without-strings-attached.html">some</a> <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/08/28/the-benefits-of-cash-without-conditions/">press</a> in the past year, and this marks the
first thorough study of GiveDirectly. I think the promising results of the
study hold exciting potential for a new paradigm of charity-giving for the
poor.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In brief, this report demonstrates that UCTs have large potential to improve
the lives of the impoverished, especially those who primarily struggle from
a lack of income. In a RCT conducted in poor villages in Western Kenya, the
study randomized UCTs along three dimensions: whether it is paid to the
husband or wife of the household, the payment schedule, and the total amount
paid. Haushofer and Shapiro, the authors of the study, are able to show that
their UCTs allow households to build assets (particularly in household repairs
and accumulation of livestock), increase consumption, reduce hunger, increase
business profits, and improve overall happiness and well-being. The money was
not spent on alcohol or tobacco &mdash; one of the historical concerns with giving
poor people money directly, as opposed to in-kind services. Notably, the study
was not able to demonstrate any change in education or health during the time
period of the study. Of course, there are some minor concerns with the study,
as with nearly any study, but it seems like experts are generally <a href="http://chrisblattman.com/2013/10/25/and-the-cashonistas-rejoice/">happy</a>
with the methodology and results.</p>

<p>For an overview of the current literature and state of the field on UCTs,
take a look at this excellent <a href="http://www.economist.com/news/international/21588385-giving-money-directly-poor-people-works-surprisingly-well-it-cannot-deal">article</a> by the Economist, which does
a good job of reviewing much of the academic literature at this point and
giving a sense of the continuing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conditional_cash_transfer#Unconditional_versus_conditional_cash_transfers">debate</a> between conditional cash transfers
(CCTs) and UCTs. Conditional cash transfers have shown to be effective, and
have become a favored tool by policymakers around the world to support
impoverished households while encouraging good behavior, such as sending
children to school. Progresa and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oportunidades">Oportunidades</a>, CCT programs started
by the government of Mexico in the late 90s, were some of the earliest
large-scale CCT programs, and their successes have engendered more programs
like it around the world. For a detailed analysis of the impact of Progresa in
Mexico, take a look at this <a href="http://www.ifpri.org/publication/impact-progresa-health">report</a>. Note however that it is
a policy report, not a peer-reviewed journal article, and so it may be
somewhat less objective. For a more rigorous comparison between CCTs and UCTs,
take a look at <a href="http://qje.oxfordjournals.org/content/126/4/1709.full.pdf">&ldquo;Cash or Condition? Evidence From a Cash Transfer Experiment&rdquo;
by Baird et al.</a>, a 2011 paper published in the Quarterly Journal of
Economics (might be paywalled).</p>

<p>I was impressed by the use of technology in GiveDirectly&rsquo;s operation, from the
use of satelite imaging and Amazon Mechanical Turk to identify poor villages
by the material of roofs (thatched vs. iron) to the use of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M-Pesa">M-Pesa</a> for
the cash transfers themselves. I have long seen M-Pesa as a very exciting
opportunity for social interventions to provide monetary gifts or incentives
in a low-cost and scalable manner.</p>

<p>In the same way that the positive results of Progresa and Oportunidades at the
turn of the millenium helped to kick off a wave of CCT programs, I believe
that the strength of this study could similarly result in new UCT
interventions in poor regions of the world. UCT programs appear to be
effective in improving social outcomes, seem to be cheaper to run
(GiveDirectly reported that 92.1% of their donations were transferred to
recipients), and most of all, respect the autonomy and agency of the poor to
make their own decisions about their lives. I am eager to hear more about how
the research in this area continues to progress.</p>

<p>Update: David McKenzie on the World Bank Impact Evaluations blog has also
posted <a href="http://blogs.worldbank.org/impactevaluations/some-thoughts-give-directly-impact-evaluation">his thoughts</a> on the report.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
