<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: education | Brandon Liu]]></title>
  <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/categories/education/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://branliu.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-21T21:12:06-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://branliu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Liu]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandon.k.liu@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Which Non-Technical Classes at Harvard Should a Technical Major Really Consider Taking?]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2012/08/29/which-non-technical-classes-at-harvard-should-a-technical-major-really-consider-taking/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-29T09:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2012/08/29/which-non-technical-classes-at-harvard-should-a-technical-major-really-consider-taking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reposting my answer to
<a href="http://www.quora.com/Harvard-College/Which-non-technical-classes-at-Harvard-should-a-technical-major-really-consider-taking">http://www.quora.com/Harvard-College/Which-non-technical-classes-at-Harvard-should-a-technical-major-really-consider-taking</a></p>

<p><strong>Question</strong>: What non-technical classes at Harvard should a technical major
really consider taking?</p>

<p>I’ll suggest a few classes, but I’m going to focus on proposing a <strong>framework</strong> for
thinking about what non-technical classes would be most valuable for you to
take as a technical major. After all, every person is unique and would enjoy
their own particular set of classes!</p>

<p>I see at least three distinct reasons why you would want to take
a non-technical class. But I’d like to focus on the first one, because
I believe it’s the most important one to spend time thinking about. If you
don’t read everything, at least read this first section.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>1. How are you going to apply and utilize your technical major?</h2>

<p>A few notes before I begin:</p>

<ul>
<li>This question is especially pertinent for those in computer science, as it’s
a technical skill that today can be applied to advance or revolutionize nearly
any industry. But this should be worth thinking about for other majors as
well.</li>
<li>This question isn’t as important if you’re planning on research or academia
post-graduation, because your options are not as wide and diverse (as far as
I can tell)</li>
<li>Finally, I’m going to be writing from the perspective of a CS major, because
I’ve thought about this from that perspective the most.</li>
</ul>


<p>As a Harvard student with a technical major, you have two enormous luxuries
due to your first-rate intellect, your technical skillset, and your Harvard
degree:</p>

<ol>
<li>You have a lot of options for choosing a career and industry, and so you have
the opportunity to do something you truly love and are passionate about.</li>
<li>If you devote yourself, you can leave a lasting contribution to whatever it is
you set your heart and mind on.</li>
</ol>


<p>But the big question is, what industry is that going to be? <strong>In what field will
I be happiest applying my technical skills? And what cause do I desire most to
advance within my lifetime?</strong> Do I want to be crusader in genomics and
personalized medicine, and be a part of the individualized, genetically-based
cure for cancer? Do I want to be a champion for human rights worldwide, and
utilize technology to tackle underserved needs in impoverished communities? Or
shall I become a leader in consumer technology and radically transform the way
people connect and communicate?</p>

<p><strong>I strongly believe that you can be any of these things, if you so have the
will and desire.</strong> What will you want to be? I still have no idea where I will
find my calling, but thankfully, college is perhaps the best place possible to
determine where I will find that highly-sought intersection of <strong>talent,
passion, and impact</strong>: the lifelong work that I excel at, that I love doing, and
that will make the world a better place. Harvard is filled with endless
opportunities and packed with the brightest people in every field imaginable
with big ambitions. And if you take the initiative, you can learn whatever it
is you want, and best of all, you can back out at anytime and start over again
with something new with very little friction (compared with post-graduation).</p>

<p>So, what to do? Your technical major will give you the raw skills needed for
the job, but it will <strong>not</strong> tell you how you should be using those skills, what
industry you should enter, or what cause you should advance. I believe that
the best way to find your cause is to <strong>explore different domains and get
exposed to the big problems ahead. Take classes in different fields, and think
about how (and whether) your technical skills can be applied in those
fields.</strong> Curious about education technology? Take something like US35:
Dilemmas of Equity and Excellence in American K-12 Education. Global health?
Maybe SW25: Case Studies in Global Health. Government? How about DPI-682:
Solving Problems Using Technology (HKS/GSD)?</p>

<p>Get exposed to all sorts of problems, needs, and opportunities in this world,
because there are a lot, and sometimes we don’t realize it because we have
such privileged lives. Discover a cause that you’re passionate about, whether
it’s that no mother worldwide has to be afraid to die while giving birth, or
that every child has the opportunity for a solid education. If you like the
class, try getting an internship and getting some real-life exposure to the
kind of work you would be doing. Find your calling.</p>

<p>I won’t say as much for the last two sections, not because they’re not as
important, but because I think they’re more self-evident.</p>

<h2>2. Obtain the foundations for the liberal arts education. Learn what any highly-educated person should know.</h2>

<p>I won’t make an exhaustive list here, but here are some things that I think
any highly-educated person should strive to understand. You don’t have to
know all of them, but the more is better! And of course, these are just
some of my opinions and you don’t have to agree — discuss with your
friends, respected colleagues, and mentors!</p>

<ul>
<li>Basic macroeconomic theory (Ec 10, Ec1010b)</li>
<li>How the American political system works (Gov 30, but seems to be a so-so
class)</li>
<li>Some philosophy; Ancient Greek philosophy is very foundational and perhaps
the most referenced (Phil 7)</li>
<li>Some history, take your pick (Hist 1011 and SW14 I’ve heard are good, but
there are plenty of good courses)</li>
<li>A few of the “Great Books”</li>
<li>General biology, general chemistry, and general physics</li>
<li>Basic statistics and probability</li>
</ul>


<p>It should be easier to determine what classes are good once you’ve narrowed
it down to a particular subject. Ask a concentrator in that field.</p>

<h2>3. Broaden your horizons and get out of your comfort zone</h2>

<p>At least once, take something totally out there just to expand your mind
a bit. It’s easy to learn about things you know you don’t know, but it can
often be quite hard to learn about what you don’t know you don’t know. But
becoming a well-educated and worldly person is all about the latter, and
this is one way to address that!</p>

<p>Classes about a different ethnicity or culture, past civilizations,
a foreign language, history of a time period you’re unfamiliar with, or
a field you think you wouldn’t be good at tend to be good for this. Look at
Q scores or ask friends, and find a course our of your comfort zone with
a phenomenal professor.</p>

<p>Do let me know if that was helpful, or if you have any comments,
disagreements, or questions. I spend a lot of time thinking about this and
I’m continually refining my philosophy. And what better way to do that than
to write and discuss? Enjoy! :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Education for a Successful Entrepreneur]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2011/10/23/the-education-for-a-successful-entrepreneur/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-23T17:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2011/10/23/the-education-for-a-successful-entrepreneur</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spend a lot of time thinking about how I can make the best use of my time,
given my circumstances and where I am in life, and one of the most important
things that I&rsquo;ve had to think about is the division of time between school and
entrepreneurship. Given that I&rsquo;m passionate about entrepreneurship and deeply
involved on campus, it would make sense for me to be spending much of my free
time working on projects, generating ideas, and practicing entrepreneurship.
After all, school is a wonderful time to work on a startup, because you don&rsquo;t
need to be making a salary, you have so many talented and ambitious peers, and
in the worst case of your startup failing, you can always fall back to your
schoolwork.</p>

<p>But this semester, I&rsquo;ve made a deliberate effort to cut down on my projects and
entrepreneurial activities in order to focus on schoolwork. I&rsquo;ve thought a lot
and there are many reasons why I&rsquo;ve made this decision to focus more on
schoolwork, and one of those reasons is that I believe entrepreneurship is
nothing more than a means to an end, and not an end in itself, as many think.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>What is entrepreneurship? I love the practice of starting off these
definitional discussions with a Wikipedia quote.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Entrepreneurship is the act of being an entrepreneur, which can be defined as<br/>&ldquo;one who undertakes innovations, finance and business acumen in an effort to<br/>transform innovations into economic goods&rdquo;.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Although not everyone may agree with this precise definition, at least it
serves to lend some concreteness to this notion of entrepreneurship that we are
discussing. But anyway, a precise definition is not necessary for what I want
to explore here.</p>

<p>So, given this definition, what does an entrepreneur need to know in order to
be successful? Yes, as according to Wikipedia&rsquo;s definition, business and
financial acumen are indeed needed. This is where many people see
entrepreneurship start and end: the business skills of building a product,
positioning yourself to a market, and growing a company as well as the
financial skills of raising money, managing capital, and turning profits. These
are all indeed the skills required of any competent entrepreneur, but I believe
that they are not the ones that lie at the heart of entrepreneurship. Just as
Disney may be incredible at designing amusement parks, creating animations, and
composing music, all those skills are secondary to what lies at the heart of
what Disney does and why it is so successful: making people happy by delivering
a magical experience.</p>

<p>If you are without a deep understanding the core of what you want to do and how
to do it, all the peripheral skills fall to the wayside and become meaningless.
And so I believe that becoming a successful entrepreneur isn&rsquo;t just about
attending workshops on raising your seed round of funding or mastering the art
of the pitch. The heart of entrepreneurship lies in innovation, in discovering
and understanding a problem that is deeply important to people to society. It
lies in having the foresight and vision to see the world differently and in
having the domain skills and expertise to forge the road ahead to create the
future you see. Every entrepreneur is passionate about a different problem and
has deep expertise in what they&rsquo;re working on, which is why there is no
entrepreneurial class or conference or forum out there that can tell you what
sort of innovation you should be working on and how you&rsquo;ll succeed. Only you
can find that on your own.</p>

<p>But that is what an education is for. You dive deep into a domain so that
you&rsquo;re prepared to be a leader in your field and to see what it&rsquo;s like to be at
the edge of human knowledge. You study history (not necessarily the history of
civilizations, but perhaps the history of other things, like technology) and
learn about the past so that you may better see into the future, because you
discover that history repeats itself. You study a breadth of subjects to know
more about the world we live in and you learn from the innovations in every
field because oftentimes the best innovations come from somewhere outside your
domain. You challenge yourself by studying hard theoretical subjects like math
or philosophy not for their applications, but because the intellectual rigor
will train your mind to be learn quickly, process rapidly, and see a bit
further into the future by understanding the implications of all that you are
exposed to.</p>

<p>This is why an education is important, especially for those who wish to be
successful in entrepreneurship and create something truly innovative &ndash;
something that requires foresight, knowledge, and lots of hard work. The other
skills have their place and their time to be learned, but you must focus on
what is important first. Successful entrepreneurs aren&rsquo;t lucky; they know
exactly what they are doing and they&rsquo;ve prepared for it, which is why they
succeed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
