<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: entrepreneurship | Brandon Liu]]></title>
  <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/categories/entrepreneurship/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://branliu.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-25T10:56:07-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://branliu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Liu]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandon.k.liu@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Judgment of Social Media Entrepreneurship]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2012/06/04/judgment-of-social-media-entrepreneurship/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-04T01:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2012/06/04/judgment-of-social-media-entrepreneurship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In recent times, it seems that there has been continual negativity against
social media and social network-based entrepreneurship. They&rsquo;ve been
continually criticized for adding minimal value to society and being
opportunistic. Other times, they&rsquo;re viewed as young people who just want to
start a company for the sake of starting a company. Indeed, I agree that social
media and social network-based problems are not the most important issues that
our society faces today. I think that much of the criticism of the changed VC
landscape and the resulting short-termed thinking of investors is quite valid,
but I believe that the criticism sometimes goes a little far when it begins to
condemn the individuals who are starting these companies (which I&rsquo;ll refer to
for the rest of this post as social media startups).</p>

<p>The primary criticism of social media startups is that they are not adding much
value to society or the economy, and that their talents, capital, and efforts
would be much better spent solving &ldquo;real&rdquo; problems like education, energy, or
our healthcare system. While this is certainly true, it&rsquo;s also quite an unfair
criticism to make. Before giving any proper critique, one should always
consider the likely alternatives to the object of criticism &mdash; or else they
risk wasting their breath on something that can&rsquo;t be easily changed or being
unfair by criticizing something that, although flawed, turns out to be the
better than most other options. I believe that most criticism of social media
startups fails to do the latter.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It is true that entrepreneurs working on social media startups could be working
on harder, more meaningful problems, but in reality it&rsquo;s much more likely that
wouldn&rsquo;t be doing either. Starting a company is quite difficult, and if they
weren&rsquo;t working on their social media startup, they would probably be at a
regular job at some company or startup, perhaps at sort of marketing, sales, or
business development role. Honestly, given that alternative, starting a company
creates much more value: It creates jobs and generates value for businesses or
consumers. I think many people jump on the bandwagon to knock on social media
startups and didn&rsquo;t take the time to really consider what the alternative would
be.</p>

<p>Most importantly of all, critics fail to realize what the social media startup
sets up the entrepreneurship for in his or her future. Most successful
entrepreneurs after having exited their company will return to start another
business, but with greater aspirations to make more impact and create an even
greater legacy. Having already achieved success and financial freedom, these
entrepreneurs will now invest their knowledge, experience, and capital to
tackle more meaningful problems in society.</p>

<p>It seems absurd that we should condemn these entrepreneurs for not attempting
difficult problems that most of us would not even attempt! We hold them to much
too high of a standard, when most of us allow ourselves to get away without the
greatest of ambitions. Rather, we should give them our encouragement and
support, so that they may grow, learn, and succeed in order to continue to
contribute more and more to society in meaningful ways as time passes. Wouldn&rsquo;t
we want the same for ourselves? After all, it&rsquo;s always hard work to create
value.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How the 'Team' page differs in Biotech vs Web Startups]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2012/05/18/how-the-team-page-differs-in-biotech-vs-web-startups/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-18T18:04:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2012/05/18/how-the-team-page-differs-in-biotech-vs-web-startups</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been spending more time exploring the biotechnology startup world lately,
and it&rsquo;s quite interesting to see its many differences from the consumer web
startup world that I&rsquo;ve become familiar with. In particular, I&rsquo;ve noticed many
ways in which their executive teams differ in their structure and presentation
on websites.</p>

<p>In this post, I&rsquo;m going to list some observations that I&rsquo;ve made, and then give
some explanations that will hopefully account for these observations. I&rsquo;ve
picked a few startup team pages that I&rsquo;ll be basing my observations on.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Biotech:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://foundationmedicine.com/about-management-team.php">http://foundationmedicine.com/about-management-team.php</a></li>
<li><a href="http://h3biomedicine.com/about_us/leadership.asp">http://h3biomedicine.com/about_us/leadership.asp</a></li>
<li><a href="http://cadencebiomedical.com/about-us/management-team/">http://cadencebiomedical.com/about-us/management-team/</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.spiralgenetics.com/team">http://www.spiralgenetics.com/team</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Web:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://asana.com/team">http://asana.com/team</a></li>
<li><a href="http://pinterest.com/about/team/">http://pinterest.com/about/team/</a></li>
<li><a href="http://learnboost.com/info/about/">http://learnboost.com/info/about/</a></li>
<li><a href="http://stripe.com/about">http://stripe.com/about</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.qwiki.com/about-us">http://www.qwiki.com/about-us</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Observations</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>Biotech startups have &lsquo;heftier&rsquo; titles. Web startups have much simpler
titles or no titles at all. The biotech startups have multiple C-level
executives, SVPs, VPs, and Directors. On the other hand, if you look at the web
startups, you sometimes can&rsquo;t even tell who the founders are.</p></li>
<li><p>Biotech startups show only the top-level executive and management teams. Web
startups tend to show their entire team, and they don&rsquo;t differentiate between
different roles. Technial and non-technical roles are all placed equally.</p></li>
<li><p>The images of all the biotech team members are taken in formal attire,
whereas all of the web startup team pictures are in informal clothing.</p></li>
<li><p>Biotech startups heavily emphasize the advanced degrees and educational
background of their management team. Most web startup team members don&rsquo;t have
advanced degrees, and educational background is often left out.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>The Differences</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>The biggest difference between biotech and web startups that results in
these observations is size. In general, biotech startups need a lot more
manpower and funding than web startups to get off the ground. As a result,
these larger biotech startups require a larger management team to deal with a
multidisciplinary team of scientists, engineers, and business people.</p></li>
<li><p>The problems that most biotech startups are deeper and more complex than
what the <strong>average</strong> web startup is working on. It seems that PhDs are
generally necessary to make the scientific breakthrough that will drive the
growth of a biotech startup. In contrast, many brilliant software engineers and
entrepreneurs don&rsquo;t even have a college degree! The average person probably
won&rsquo;t understand what a biotech startup is working on, but will have a pretty
good grasp of what most web startups are working on.</p></li>
<li><p>As a result, the average age at a biotech startup is slightly older, as most
have completed advanced degree programs. This seems to lead to a slightly more
formal environment.</p></li>
<li><p>Nearly all biotech startups have tight relationships with academic
institutions and large biomedical or pharmaceutical corporations, and as a
result, seem to be influenced by a more bureaucratic kind of culture.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>As I&rsquo;ve been learning about this biotech space, it&rsquo;s been interesting to notice
its differences from the web startup world. I&rsquo;ve only been looking into the
biotech startup for a few months now, and so I don&rsquo;t really know the
intricacies of how the biotech startup space looks like. As I continue to
explore this space further, I&rsquo;m sure I&rsquo;ll continue to learn more and understand
better the influential factors that make biotech a very different space than
the Silicon Valley startup culture.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Education for a Successful Entrepreneur]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2011/10/23/the-education-for-a-successful-entrepreneur/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-23T17:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2011/10/23/the-education-for-a-successful-entrepreneur</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spend a lot of time thinking about how I can make the best use of my time,
given my circumstances and where I am in life, and one of the most important
things that I&rsquo;ve had to think about is the division of time between school and
entrepreneurship. Given that I&rsquo;m passionate about entrepreneurship and deeply
involved on campus, it would make sense for me to be spending much of my free
time working on projects, generating ideas, and practicing entrepreneurship.
After all, school is a wonderful time to work on a startup, because you don&rsquo;t
need to be making a salary, you have so many talented and ambitious peers, and
in the worst case of your startup failing, you can always fall back to your
schoolwork.</p>

<p>But this semester, I&rsquo;ve made a deliberate effort to cut down on my projects and
entrepreneurial activities in order to focus on schoolwork. I&rsquo;ve thought a lot
and there are many reasons why I&rsquo;ve made this decision to focus more on
schoolwork, and one of those reasons is that I believe entrepreneurship is
nothing more than a means to an end, and not an end in itself, as many think.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>What is entrepreneurship? I love the practice of starting off these
definitional discussions with a Wikipedia quote.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Entrepreneurship is the act of being an entrepreneur, which can be defined as<br/>&ldquo;one who undertakes innovations, finance and business acumen in an effort to<br/>transform innovations into economic goods&rdquo;.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Although not everyone may agree with this precise definition, at least it
serves to lend some concreteness to this notion of entrepreneurship that we are
discussing. But anyway, a precise definition is not necessary for what I want
to explore here.</p>

<p>So, given this definition, what does an entrepreneur need to know in order to
be successful? Yes, as according to Wikipedia&rsquo;s definition, business and
financial acumen are indeed needed. This is where many people see
entrepreneurship start and end: the business skills of building a product,
positioning yourself to a market, and growing a company as well as the
financial skills of raising money, managing capital, and turning profits. These
are all indeed the skills required of any competent entrepreneur, but I believe
that they are not the ones that lie at the heart of entrepreneurship. Just as
Disney may be incredible at designing amusement parks, creating animations, and
composing music, all those skills are secondary to what lies at the heart of
what Disney does and why it is so successful: making people happy by delivering
a magical experience.</p>

<p>If you are without a deep understanding the core of what you want to do and how
to do it, all the peripheral skills fall to the wayside and become meaningless.
And so I believe that becoming a successful entrepreneur isn&rsquo;t just about
attending workshops on raising your seed round of funding or mastering the art
of the pitch. The heart of entrepreneurship lies in innovation, in discovering
and understanding a problem that is deeply important to people to society. It
lies in having the foresight and vision to see the world differently and in
having the domain skills and expertise to forge the road ahead to create the
future you see. Every entrepreneur is passionate about a different problem and
has deep expertise in what they&rsquo;re working on, which is why there is no
entrepreneurial class or conference or forum out there that can tell you what
sort of innovation you should be working on and how you&rsquo;ll succeed. Only you
can find that on your own.</p>

<p>But that is what an education is for. You dive deep into a domain so that
you&rsquo;re prepared to be a leader in your field and to see what it&rsquo;s like to be at
the edge of human knowledge. You study history (not necessarily the history of
civilizations, but perhaps the history of other things, like technology) and
learn about the past so that you may better see into the future, because you
discover that history repeats itself. You study a breadth of subjects to know
more about the world we live in and you learn from the innovations in every
field because oftentimes the best innovations come from somewhere outside your
domain. You challenge yourself by studying hard theoretical subjects like math
or philosophy not for their applications, but because the intellectual rigor
will train your mind to be learn quickly, process rapidly, and see a bit
further into the future by understanding the implications of all that you are
exposed to.</p>

<p>This is why an education is important, especially for those who wish to be
successful in entrepreneurship and create something truly innovative &ndash;
something that requires foresight, knowledge, and lots of hard work. The other
skills have their place and their time to be learned, but you must focus on
what is important first. Successful entrepreneurs aren&rsquo;t lucky; they know
exactly what they are doing and they&rsquo;ve prepared for it, which is why they
succeed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
