<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Brandon Liu]]></title>
  <link href="http://branliu.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://branliu.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-31T22:05:52-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://branliu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Liu]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandon.k.liu@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Which Non-Technical Classes at Harvard Should a Technical Major Really Consider Taking?]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2012/08/29/which-non-technical-classes-at-harvard-should-a-technical-major-really-consider-taking/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-29T09:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2012/08/29/which-non-technical-classes-at-harvard-should-a-technical-major-really-consider-taking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Reposting my answer to
<a href="http://www.quora.com/Harvard-College/Which-non-technical-classes-at-Harvard-should-a-technical-major-really-consider-taking">http://www.quora.com/Harvard-College/Which-non-technical-classes-at-Harvard-should-a-technical-major-really-consider-taking</a></p>

<p><strong>Question</strong>: What non-technical classes at Harvard should a technical major
really consider taking?</p>

<p>I’ll suggest a few classes, but I’m going to focus on proposing a <strong>framework</strong> for
thinking about what non-technical classes would be most valuable for you to
take as a technical major. After all, every person is unique and would enjoy
their own particular set of classes!</p>

<p>I see at least three distinct reasons why you would want to take
a non-technical class. But I’d like to focus on the first one, because
I believe it’s the most important one to spend time thinking about. If you
don’t read everything, at least read this first section.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>1. How are you going to apply and utilize your technical major?</h2>

<p>A few notes before I begin:</p>

<ul>
<li>This question is especially pertinent for those in computer science, as it’s
a technical skill that today can be applied to advance or revolutionize nearly
any industry. But this should be worth thinking about for other majors as
well.</li>
<li>This question isn’t as important if you’re planning on research or academia
post-graduation, because your options are not as wide and diverse (as far as
I can tell)</li>
<li>Finally, I’m going to be writing from the perspective of a CS major, because
I’ve thought about this from that perspective the most.</li>
</ul>


<p>As a Harvard student with a technical major, you have two enormous luxuries
due to your first-rate intellect, your technical skillset, and your Harvard
degree:</p>

<ol>
<li>You have a lot of options for choosing a career and industry, and so you have
the opportunity to do something you truly love and are passionate about.</li>
<li>If you devote yourself, you can leave a lasting contribution to whatever it is
you set your heart and mind on.</li>
</ol>


<p>But the big question is, what industry is that going to be? <strong>In what field will
I be happiest applying my technical skills? And what cause do I desire most to
advance within my lifetime?</strong> Do I want to be crusader in genomics and
personalized medicine, and be a part of the individualized, genetically-based
cure for cancer? Do I want to be a champion for human rights worldwide, and
utilize technology to tackle underserved needs in impoverished communities? Or
shall I become a leader in consumer technology and radically transform the way
people connect and communicate?</p>

<p><strong>I strongly believe that you can be any of these things, if you so have the
will and desire.</strong> What will you want to be? I still have no idea where I will
find my calling, but thankfully, college is perhaps the best place possible to
determine where I will find that highly-sought intersection of <strong>talent,
passion, and impact</strong>: the lifelong work that I excel at, that I love doing, and
that will make the world a better place. Harvard is filled with endless
opportunities and packed with the brightest people in every field imaginable
with big ambitions. And if you take the initiative, you can learn whatever it
is you want, and best of all, you can back out at anytime and start over again
with something new with very little friction (compared with post-graduation).</p>

<p>So, what to do? Your technical major will give you the raw skills needed for
the job, but it will <strong>not</strong> tell you how you should be using those skills, what
industry you should enter, or what cause you should advance. I believe that
the best way to find your cause is to <strong>explore different domains and get
exposed to the big problems ahead. Take classes in different fields, and think
about how (and whether) your technical skills can be applied in those
fields.</strong> Curious about education technology? Take something like US35:
Dilemmas of Equity and Excellence in American K-12 Education. Global health?
Maybe SW25: Case Studies in Global Health. Government? How about DPI-682:
Solving Problems Using Technology (HKS/GSD)?</p>

<p>Get exposed to all sorts of problems, needs, and opportunities in this world,
because there are a lot, and sometimes we don’t realize it because we have
such privileged lives. Discover a cause that you’re passionate about, whether
it’s that no mother worldwide has to be afraid to die while giving birth, or
that every child has the opportunity for a solid education. If you like the
class, try getting an internship and getting some real-life exposure to the
kind of work you would be doing. Find your calling.</p>

<p>I won’t say as much for the last two sections, not because they’re not as
important, but because I think they’re more self-evident.</p>

<h2>2. Obtain the foundations for the liberal arts education. Learn what any highly-educated person should know.</h2>

<p>I won’t make an exhaustive list here, but here are some things that I think
any highly-educated person should strive to understand. You don’t have to
know all of them, but the more is better! And of course, these are just
some of my opinions and you don’t have to agree — discuss with your
friends, respected colleagues, and mentors!</p>

<ul>
<li>Basic macroeconomic theory (Ec 10, Ec1010b)</li>
<li>How the American political system works (Gov 30, but seems to be a so-so
class)</li>
<li>Some philosophy; Ancient Greek philosophy is very foundational and perhaps
the most referenced (Phil 7)</li>
<li>Some history, take your pick (Hist 1011 and SW14 I’ve heard are good, but
there are plenty of good courses)</li>
<li>A few of the “Great Books”</li>
<li>General biology, general chemistry, and general physics</li>
<li>Basic statistics and probability</li>
</ul>


<p>It should be easier to determine what classes are good once you’ve narrowed
it down to a particular subject. Ask a concentrator in that field.</p>

<h2>3. Broaden your horizons and get out of your comfort zone</h2>

<p>At least once, take something totally out there just to expand your mind
a bit. It’s easy to learn about things you know you don’t know, but it can
often be quite hard to learn about what you don’t know you don’t know. But
becoming a well-educated and worldly person is all about the latter, and
this is one way to address that!</p>

<p>Classes about a different ethnicity or culture, past civilizations,
a foreign language, history of a time period you’re unfamiliar with, or
a field you think you wouldn’t be good at tend to be good for this. Look at
Q scores or ask friends, and find a course our of your comfort zone with
a phenomenal professor.</p>

<p>Do let me know if that was helpful, or if you have any comments,
disagreements, or questions. I spend a lot of time thinking about this and
I’m continually refining my philosophy. And what better way to do that than
to write and discuss? Enjoy! :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simulating the Life and Death of Last Names: Initial Findings]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2012/07/02/simulating-the-life-and-death-of-last-names-initial-findings/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-02T21:50:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2012/07/02/simulating-the-life-and-death-of-last-names-initial-findings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few months ago, my friend put forth an interesting question: What happens
to the number of last names over time? It is common to hear about a family
name dying with a last descendant who never had any children. That suggests
that it is possible that in the future, we will all have just one of a handful
of last names, as most of them will have died off. Yet, I would expect that if
it could happen, it should have happened by now, or at the very least, I would
be able to discern some kind of sign suggesting a trend toward fewer last
names. But the number and diversity of last names on Earth is quite
remarkable, and it&rsquo;s still a uncommon thing for two unrelated people to meet
and have the same last name.</p>

<p>Anyway, in the spirit of curiosity, I decided to write a small Ruby script
that would simulate the progression of last names over many generations, just
to see what the end result might be. I had an enjoyable time exploring the
problem, and ended up with some interesting results.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Basic assumptions for my model</h2>

<p>First, I had to model the way that last names are passed down in order to
write a simulation. Here are the basic assumptions that I made:</p>

<ul>
<li>Names are always inherited from the father</li>
<li>Boys and girls are born with equal probability</li>
<li>Each generation, every woman gives birth to at least two children</li>
<li>Each woman procreates with exactly one man randomly sampled from the male
population</li>
<li>A man can procreate with multiple women, or with none. A man is randomly
selected for each woman, so a man could be selected multiple times, or not
at all.</li>
</ul>


<p>I also decided to cut off each simulation after 1500 generations, which
was a reasonable amount of time for my computer to run a few simulations, and
would also effectively simulate about 45 thousand years of human life, under
the assumption that a generation is 30 years.</p>

<p>Of course, many of these assumptions are not particular representative of the
real world, but they provide a set of rules that we can start experimenting
with.</p>

<h2>Observations</h2>

<p>I played around with the problem a bit, trying different starting population
sizes and different ways to determine the number of children a couple would
have. Here&rsquo;s what I found.</p>

<h3>Last Names in the End Game</h3>

<ul>
<li>The number of last names would quickly dwindle, but often by the 1000th
generation they would stabilize at some number between 2 and 8. Over 100
separate trials, here is the histogram of the number of last names in
existence after 1500 generations.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://chart.apis.google.com/chart?chxr=0,2,8|1,0,30&amp;chxs=0,676767,11.5,1,lt,676767|1,676767,11.5,0,lt,676767&amp;chxt=x,y&amp;chbh=a&amp;chs=400x273&amp;cht=bvs&amp;chd=s:Qxr0USE&amp;chdlp=b&amp;chtt=Histogram+for+number+of+remaining+last+names" alt="Histogram for number of remaining last names" /></p>

<h3>Population Growth</h3>

<ul>
<li>If I set the number of children per couple at two, then the population stays
roughly stable, with some moderate fluctuations due to randomness in the
gender of the children being born. If I have a starting population of 50 men
and 50 women, then they die out pretty quickly because the population runs
out of men within a few generations.</li>
<li>So in order for an initial population of 50 to survive, I have to set the
number of children to be greater than 3, to ensure that they don&rsquo;t die out
due to random fluctuations. But because three children are being born for
every two adults, the population experience exponential growth, and the
population size soon becomes too large for my computer to handle.</li>
<li>I end up settling for an intial population of 5000 men and 5000 women, which
is large enough to withstand the random fluctuations to survive.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Analysis</h2>

<p>The biggest result of this vastly simplified model is that the last names
indeed diminish down to some small number of last names that becomes stable.
It is interesting to see this, because it suggests that it is a potential
outcome, although my intuition says that it&rsquo;s unlikely due to the unrealistic
assumptions of the underlying model.</p>

<p>On the other hand, some estimates say that 85 percent of China&rsquo;s population
have one of 100 surnames. After all, the Chinese people do call themselves
&ldquo;Old 100 surnames&rdquo; (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baixing">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baixing</a>). But doesn&rsquo;t seem to
be the case in most parts of the world.</p>

<p>It isn&rsquo;t immediately clear why in particular the model doesn&rsquo;t match what I&rsquo;ve
observed in the real world. If it&rsquo;s one or more of my underlying assumptions
for the model, it isn&rsquo;t clear which of them result in the difference.</p>

<p>It is certainly possible that my simulation, which approximates 45,000 years,
does actually predict the future, and that our society is still too early in
the process to have reached the end state. After all, I don&rsquo;t think that the
concept of last names have existed in society for more than a few thousand
years.</p>

<p>In particular, it is interesting to note a significant flaw in my model. Due
to the way that I&rsquo;ve simulated the pairing of couples, a large portion of men
actually don&rsquo;t get a chance to mate at all in each generation! When the
population of men and women are equal in size, the expected proportion of the
male population that doesn&rsquo;t get picked by any woman is roughly <em>1/e</em>, or
0.368. If there are <em>n</em> men and <em>n</em> women, then the probability that a man is
not picked by any woman is simply <em>((n-1)/n)<sup>n</sup></em>, which approaches <em>1/e</em> as <em>n</em>
gets large.</p>

<h2>Further Exploration</h2>

<p>When I have time, I would like to spend some more time with this problem to
better answer the questions that still remain. Here are some potential avenues
for exploration.</p>

<ul>
<li>Devising and implementing a more accurate model of how couples are actually
formed, so that there isn&rsquo;t a significant portion of the male population
that is left out each generation.</li>
<li>Experiment with desirability: Give each person some measure of desirability,
which affects their rate of procreation and influences their children&rsquo;s
desriability.</li>
<li>Play with different lengths of simulations. Perhaps end the simulation
only after the number of last names stay stable for some number of
generations. Maybe all simulations will eventually end with two last names,
or perhaps there could be different stable outcomes.</li>
<li>Play with randomly adding new last names throughout the process</li>
</ul>


<p>I may post a followup post at some point with some further results after
I spend some more time with this experiment!</p>

<h2>The code</h2>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
<span class='line-number'>32</span>
<span class='line-number'>33</span>
<span class='line-number'>34</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="c1">#!/usr/bin/env ruby</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">simulate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">num_start_people</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">5000</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">males</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">.num_start_people</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">to_a</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">females</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">.num_start_people</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">to_a</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">new_males</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">[]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">new_females</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">[]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">step</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kp">loop</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">step</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">females</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">size</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">times</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">|</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nb">name</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">males</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">sample</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">num_children</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">males</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">size</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">5000</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="nb">rand</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">?</span> <span class="mi">2</span> <span class="p">:</span> <span class="mi">3</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">num_children</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">times</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="nb">rand</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="n">new_males</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="nb">name</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">else</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="n">new_females</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="nb">name</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">males</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">new_males</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">clone</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">females</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">new_females</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">clone</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">new_males</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">clear</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">new_females</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">clear</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">break</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">step</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">1500</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">males</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">uniq</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">count</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">100</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">times</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="n">simulate</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[littleBits: An Innovation in Education With Just A Little Further To Go]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2012/06/17/littlebits-an-innovation-in-education-with-just-a-little-further-to-go/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-17T20:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2012/06/17/littlebits-an-innovation-in-education-with-just-a-little-further-to-go</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of weeks ago, a friend of mine introduced me to the amazing world of
<a href="http://littlebits.cc">littleBits</a>. I had been taking an electrical
engineering course last semester, spending lots of time in lab playing with
circuits, so I was especially excited to see such an innovative product that
made it so easy for kids to explore the world of electronics and build their
own toys out of them!</p>

<p>littleBits is like LEGOs for electronics: they have a variety of different
electrical components that snap together with magnetics to create all sorts of
different circuits. For example, you could snap the power source component,
the knob component, and the LED component, and as you turn the knob, the LED
will turn dimmer and brighter. littleBits has already developed all sorts of
creative bits, as they call them, to create a wide variety of electronic
circuits, including motion sensor inputs to DC motor outputs. You can see all
of them <a href="https://community.littlebits.cc/bits">here</a></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>A thoughtful, innovative product</h2>

<p>I took some time to look through their website and think
about their product, and I&rsquo;m deeply impressed by what they&rsquo;ve been able to
create so far. Here&rsquo;s why I think littleBits is an amazing educational
product.</p>

<h3>No annoying obstacles to slow you down</h3>

<p>The most difficult thing when you start something new is often the small, but
numerous hurdles you must surpass as you begin. When you want to start
exercising, you have to find a gym, get a membership, and perhaps learn the basic
exercise movements. When you first learn to code, you may have to find the
right learning materials, install various applications, and get your
environment set up. In electronic circuits, you have to buy the right parts,
have a basic understanding of electricity (in particular Ohm&rsquo;s Law), and be
prepared to spend some frustrating time debugging your circuit. Each of
these small obstacles present opportunities for you to stop and just give up.</p>

<p>littleBits eliminates these tiny inhibitors and lowers the barrier for
children to begin playing with electronics. No more need to verify all your
breadboard connections and check your spec sheet to see that all the pins are
in the right places; littleBit&rsquo;s fantastic magentic snap ensures that your
connections are always correct! littleBits clearly worked hard to optimize on
this front, and I think their work will pay off, as younger children
have much less patience than adults, and even we have difficulty sticking
through with new things!</p>

<h3>A lower barrier to experimentation results in greater innovation</h3>

<p>The magnetic snap on the little bits allows you to quickly assemble and
disassemble the bits. This allows for children to easily experiment and build
all kinds of creative products. In the past decade, the ease with which
internet applications can now be built has resulted in an explosion in
innovation in the internet industry. Similarly, I believe littleBits will
enable many more children to create incredible toys and projects with
electronics than ever before.</p>

<h3>Quick trial and error allows for learning by exploration and discovery</h3>

<p>Most importantly, littleBits seems to have been designed for kids to learn
through exploration and discovery. I can imagine that most kids would be able
to pick up some littleBits and figure out how they work in a short amount of
time, just by putting things together and seeing how they work. I believe this
aspect of the product is perhaps most significant, because it results in
learning, without the children feeling like they&rsquo;re really learning anything
&mdash; it&rsquo;s just play to them! And that&rsquo;s the best kind of activity to foster
a life of intellectual curiosity and lifelong learning, because it
demonstrates that learning <em>is</em> fun.</p>

<h2>Still improvements to be made</h2>

<p>However, while thinking about the product, I found that there are still a few
areas in which littleBits could do better.</p>

<h3>Prohibitively expensive</h3>

<p>The biggest disappointment I had with littleBits was with their pricing. If
you buy the bits in kits, then they&rsquo;re about $9-10 per bit, and they are even
more expensive if you buy them individually. I&rsquo;m not an expert in electronics,
so it isn&rsquo;t clear to me what a reasonable price for these components would be,
but from the perspective of a consumer, littleBits is currently prohibitively
expensive. If I wanted to create a project with any moderate amount of
complexity, I&rsquo;m sure I would at least need one or two dozen bits, which would
end up costing me up to two hundred dollars! littleBits will have to bring
their prices down before they can tap into the mainstream consumer market.</p>

<h3>Memory modules will expand the range of projects</h3>

<p>I also worry that the set of bits that littleBits currently has doesn&rsquo;t offer
sufficient replay value to justify their costs. While they have a
simple model of power, input, output, and wiring modules, I would imagine that
one would quickly become bored of playing with the bits, because there
are only so many combinations that can be created.</p>

<p>What littleBits needs to do is add the fundamental concept of memory and
storage to their components. Doing so would explode the possibilities for what
could be created &mdash; the vast majority of electronic components today require
the use of memory, and the few that do not (e.g., a guitar amp) probably
couldn&rsquo;t easily be made with littleBits. Including memory would allow projects
to become stateful, opening a entire new world of applications.</p>

<h2>In Conclusion</h2>

<p>I commend the team behind littleBits for all the work they&rsquo;ve put into
creating such a simple and educational product. Simplifying a product is one
of the hardest things to do and especially so for engineers! I think
littleBits has the potential to be very successful in the future, but there
are still a few small things that I believe need to be resolved, but when they
do, I&rsquo;m sure they will have an outstanding market entrance.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Use Names in Conversation to Grow Friendships]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2012/06/11/use-names-in-conversation-to-grow-friendships/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-11T23:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2012/06/11/use-names-in-conversation-to-grow-friendships</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Oftentimes when we having a conversation with a friend, and we are telling
a story about something that happened, we will refer to other people in the
story as “my friend,” “my other friend,” and so on, avoiding mentioning their
names. The logic is that it is probably better leave out the names, as they
would confuse the listener, who probably wouldn’t remember them anyway.</p>

<p>However, I’ve found that when I’m having a conversation with a good friend,
and we’re sharing a very personal story that is important to one of us, it
distances the listener when we avoid mentioning names, and instead continually
repeat a phrase like “my friend” or “my girlfriend” throughout the story.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Whenever I tell my own personal stories, I always make sure to include the
names of the characters involved. Of course, I’ll remember to include their
relationships to me so that the listener can keep track of the story. By doing
this, I bring the listener closer into my life, so that he or she becomes more
familiar with the people who are important to me.</p>

<p>As you become closer with someone, you are able to stop mentioning people’s
relationships to you entirely, and tell stories by mentioning people only by
name. This implies that you know that the listener knows who these people are,
and that the listener is close enough to you to know. It would add a certain
degree of distance if you continually added that John was your best friend.</p>

<p>So now, whenever I am listening to a friend telling a story, I will ask him or
her to tell me the names of the characters, if he or she did not do so. It
makes the story more vivid to have names, and I feel it brings me closer into
his or her life.</p>

<p>Every conversation is a wonderful opportunity to get to know someone better,
and to become closer and stronger friends. I want to make sure I take every
change to understand my friends better and to know their lives so that I can
be there for them! And this is just one tiny thing that I can do to continue
to grow my friendships.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Judgment of Social Media Entrepreneurship]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2012/06/04/judgment-of-social-media-entrepreneurship/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-04T01:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2012/06/04/judgment-of-social-media-entrepreneurship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In recent times, it seems that there has been continual negativity against
social media and social network-based entrepreneurship. They&rsquo;ve been
continually criticized for adding minimal value to society and being
opportunistic. Other times, they&rsquo;re viewed as young people who just want to
start a company for the sake of starting a company. Indeed, I agree that social
media and social network-based problems are not the most important issues that
our society faces today. I think that much of the criticism of the changed VC
landscape and the resulting short-termed thinking of investors is quite valid,
but I believe that the criticism sometimes goes a little far when it begins to
condemn the individuals who are starting these companies (which I&rsquo;ll refer to
for the rest of this post as social media startups).</p>

<p>The primary criticism of social media startups is that they are not adding much
value to society or the economy, and that their talents, capital, and efforts
would be much better spent solving &ldquo;real&rdquo; problems like education, energy, or
our healthcare system. While this is certainly true, it&rsquo;s also quite an unfair
criticism to make. Before giving any proper critique, one should always
consider the likely alternatives to the object of criticism &mdash; or else they
risk wasting their breath on something that can&rsquo;t be easily changed or being
unfair by criticizing something that, although flawed, turns out to be the
better than most other options. I believe that most criticism of social media
startups fails to do the latter.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It is true that entrepreneurs working on social media startups could be working
on harder, more meaningful problems, but in reality it&rsquo;s much more likely that
wouldn&rsquo;t be doing either. Starting a company is quite difficult, and if they
weren&rsquo;t working on their social media startup, they would probably be at a
regular job at some company or startup, perhaps at sort of marketing, sales, or
business development role. Honestly, given that alternative, starting a company
creates much more value: It creates jobs and generates value for businesses or
consumers. I think many people jump on the bandwagon to knock on social media
startups and didn&rsquo;t take the time to really consider what the alternative would
be.</p>

<p>Most importantly of all, critics fail to realize what the social media startup
sets up the entrepreneurship for in his or her future. Most successful
entrepreneurs after having exited their company will return to start another
business, but with greater aspirations to make more impact and create an even
greater legacy. Having already achieved success and financial freedom, these
entrepreneurs will now invest their knowledge, experience, and capital to
tackle more meaningful problems in society.</p>

<p>It seems absurd that we should condemn these entrepreneurs for not attempting
difficult problems that most of us would not even attempt! We hold them to much
too high of a standard, when most of us allow ourselves to get away without the
greatest of ambitions. Rather, we should give them our encouragement and
support, so that they may grow, learn, and succeed in order to continue to
contribute more and more to society in meaningful ways as time passes. Wouldn&rsquo;t
we want the same for ourselves? After all, it&rsquo;s always hard work to create
value.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Subtle Art of Becoming a Master of Facilitating Meetings]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2012/05/25/the-subtle-art-of-becoming-a-master-of-facilitating-meetings/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-25T18:09:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2012/05/25/the-subtle-art-of-becoming-a-master-of-facilitating-meetings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What makes someone a master of facilitating meetings?</p>

<p>When people teach others how to run effective meetings, they usually cover
specific meeting techniques that can be used. Here are some of the most
commons ones:</p>

<ul>
<li>Allow everyone a chance to speak, and actively encourage reticent
participants.</li>
<li>Use an agenda, schedule each agenda item (as opposed to just listing
them), and send it out before the meeting.</li>
<li>Create a list of action items to follow up on after the meeting, with assigned
persons of responsibility and deadlines.</li>
</ul>


<p>Implementing these techniques will undoubtedly make your meetings more
effective, but I feel that these recommendations miss the high-level skills
that are often more subtle to articulate. The actions above will help anyone
become competent at running meetings, but there is much more that is needed to
become a true master at meetings.</p>

<p>Briefly, I discuss two skills I believe are core to any outstanding
meeting facilitator. While my points may be less actionable than many of the
techniques you can find online, I believe they provide a valuable framework
for evaluating yourself as an effective leader during meetings. Self-awareness
is the first step to personal growth!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I do not take the time to expand upon each point at length here, so be sure
take the time to digest each point.</p>

<h2>Facilitation</h2>

<p>To run an outstanding meeting, you must be an outstanding facilitator of
discussion. The skills involved in being an outstanding facilitator include:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Controlling the level and detail of discussion.</strong> For example, don&rsquo;t discuss
logistics when discussing strategy and vision, and vice versa. Doing so will
waste time and the meeting will lose focus.</li>
<li><strong>Controlling the time given for a discussion.</strong> Allow ample time for discussion,
but cut it off and make a decision when needed. You cannot wait for unanimity,
and you certainly cannot make everyone happy. If a decision can’t be made,
determine concrete action items to be done before a decision can be made and
move on.</li>
<li><strong>Controlling the scope of the discussion.</strong> Take on one item at a time, come to
some sort of actionable conclusion, and then move on to the next item. Don’t
allow the discussion to stray off course. New discussion items can be added to
the bottom of the agenda.</li>
<li><strong>Breaking down what is said into its core message</strong> by repeating the essence when
needed. People can be verbose and roundabout when speaking, and it often
obscures their argument to the rest of the group, and even to themselves.
Paring their thoughts down to the essential and rephrasing them to directly
address what has been said will ensure that the discussion makes progress.</li>
<li><strong>Pointing out logical fallacies</strong> when you hear them. Ad hominem, straw mans, and
appeals to majority are especially common and undesirable. Understand proper
argumentation to ensure that your decisions are based on facts.</li>
<li><strong>Being open-minded</strong> by encouraging and incorporating feedback. Allow everyone to
share their thoughts, give each careful consideration, and push ahead with the
best ones. You don’t even have to have the majority on your side – just make
sure everyone feels that their voice was heard.</li>
<li><strong>Guiding the outcome of the meeting</strong>, rather than directing it. You need your
team to be invested in the decision-making process, so that they will be
committed to the ultimate outcome.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Knowing your desired outcome</h2>

<p>No one ever consistently accomplishes anything great without setting his or
her intentions and desired outcomes. This will also help you keep your meeting
on track and on time. Running a highly effective meeting requires:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Knowing exactly why you are having the meeting and what you want to get out of
it.</strong> You must know exactly why every single agenda item is on there. What do
you want to accomplish by the end of the meeting?</li>
<li><strong>Knowing exactly why every attendee must be there.</strong> If you value people’s time,
they will value yours.</li>
<li><strong>Never holding a meeting for the sake of holding a meeting.</strong> This will be the
death of your team&rsquo;s morale and productivity. If you have a weekly meeting
planned, but there isn’t much to discuss, just cancel the meeting!</li>
</ol>


<p>Running an effective meeting is a subtle and nuanced art requiring a high
level of social awareness and focus throughout the discussion. In my opinion,
mastery of these skills is very difficult and few people have attained it. If
you want to improve yourself, pay close attention during discussions and try
to get a high-level feel for the direction, scope, and level of the discussion
without getting bogged down in what is actually being said. Develop an
intuition for guiding and facilitating discussion by leading meetings and then
self-reflecting afterward.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How the 'Team' page differs in Biotech vs Web Startups]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2012/05/18/how-the-team-page-differs-in-biotech-vs-web-startups/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-18T18:04:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2012/05/18/how-the-team-page-differs-in-biotech-vs-web-startups</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been spending more time exploring the biotechnology startup world lately,
and it&rsquo;s quite interesting to see its many differences from the consumer web
startup world that I&rsquo;ve become familiar with. In particular, I&rsquo;ve noticed many
ways in which their executive teams differ in their structure and presentation
on websites.</p>

<p>In this post, I&rsquo;m going to list some observations that I&rsquo;ve made, and then give
some explanations that will hopefully account for these observations. I&rsquo;ve
picked a few startup team pages that I&rsquo;ll be basing my observations on.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Biotech:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://foundationmedicine.com/about-management-team.php">http://foundationmedicine.com/about-management-team.php</a></li>
<li><a href="http://h3biomedicine.com/about_us/leadership.asp">http://h3biomedicine.com/about_us/leadership.asp</a></li>
<li><a href="http://cadencebiomedical.com/about-us/management-team/">http://cadencebiomedical.com/about-us/management-team/</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.spiralgenetics.com/team">http://www.spiralgenetics.com/team</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Web:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://asana.com/team">http://asana.com/team</a></li>
<li><a href="http://pinterest.com/about/team/">http://pinterest.com/about/team/</a></li>
<li><a href="http://learnboost.com/info/about/">http://learnboost.com/info/about/</a></li>
<li><a href="http://stripe.com/about">http://stripe.com/about</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.qwiki.com/about-us">http://www.qwiki.com/about-us</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Observations</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>Biotech startups have &lsquo;heftier&rsquo; titles. Web startups have much simpler
titles or no titles at all. The biotech startups have multiple C-level
executives, SVPs, VPs, and Directors. On the other hand, if you look at the web
startups, you sometimes can&rsquo;t even tell who the founders are.</p></li>
<li><p>Biotech startups show only the top-level executive and management teams. Web
startups tend to show their entire team, and they don&rsquo;t differentiate between
different roles. Technial and non-technical roles are all placed equally.</p></li>
<li><p>The images of all the biotech team members are taken in formal attire,
whereas all of the web startup team pictures are in informal clothing.</p></li>
<li><p>Biotech startups heavily emphasize the advanced degrees and educational
background of their management team. Most web startup team members don&rsquo;t have
advanced degrees, and educational background is often left out.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>The Differences</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>The biggest difference between biotech and web startups that results in
these observations is size. In general, biotech startups need a lot more
manpower and funding than web startups to get off the ground. As a result,
these larger biotech startups require a larger management team to deal with a
multidisciplinary team of scientists, engineers, and business people.</p></li>
<li><p>The problems that most biotech startups are deeper and more complex than
what the <strong>average</strong> web startup is working on. It seems that PhDs are
generally necessary to make the scientific breakthrough that will drive the
growth of a biotech startup. In contrast, many brilliant software engineers and
entrepreneurs don&rsquo;t even have a college degree! The average person probably
won&rsquo;t understand what a biotech startup is working on, but will have a pretty
good grasp of what most web startups are working on.</p></li>
<li><p>As a result, the average age at a biotech startup is slightly older, as most
have completed advanced degree programs. This seems to lead to a slightly more
formal environment.</p></li>
<li><p>Nearly all biotech startups have tight relationships with academic
institutions and large biomedical or pharmaceutical corporations, and as a
result, seem to be influenced by a more bureaucratic kind of culture.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>As I&rsquo;ve been learning about this biotech space, it&rsquo;s been interesting to notice
its differences from the web startup world. I&rsquo;ve only been looking into the
biotech startup for a few months now, and so I don&rsquo;t really know the
intricacies of how the biotech startup space looks like. As I continue to
explore this space further, I&rsquo;m sure I&rsquo;ll continue to learn more and understand
better the influential factors that make biotech a very different space than
the Silicon Valley startup culture.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Organizing your .vimrc]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2012/05/14/organizing-your-vimrc/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-14T18:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2012/05/14/organizing-your-vimrc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most .vimrc files that I’ve seen are quite long and unwieldy, often extending
to upwards of 300 lines of code. The .vimrc becomes a mess of code as it is
built up over the years, just a few lines at a time. Many people try to
resolve this issue by breaking the .vimrc down into sections, often with the
help of comments or fold markers. This makes it much easier to read, but it
isn’t a perfect solution. I still find myself having to scroll around the
.vimrc to find the line of I want to change or to find a place I can insert
a new line of vimscript.</p>

<p>There’s a much better solution for organizing the .vimrc, thanks to the
ability to source other vimscripts from within a vimscript. I’ve broken up my
own .vimrc file into 8 smaller files, and I include them into my main .vimrc
file by using the source function. Here’s what it looks like:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='vim'><span class='line'><span class="k">set</span> <span class="nb">nocompatible</span>
</span><span class='line'>behave <span class="k">xterm</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">filetype</span> plugin indent <span class="k">on</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">syntax</span> <span class="k">on</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>source $HOME<span class="sr">/.vim/</span>vimrc/filetypes.<span class="k">vim</span>
</span><span class='line'>source $HOME<span class="sr">/.vim/</span>vimrc/looks.<span class="k">vim</span>
</span><span class='line'>source $HOME<span class="sr">/.vim/</span>vimrc/mappings.<span class="k">vim</span>
</span><span class='line'>source $HOME<span class="sr">/.vim/</span>vimrc/misc.<span class="k">vim</span>
</span><span class='line'>source $HOME<span class="sr">/.vim/</span>vimrc/plugin_configs.<span class="k">vim</span>
</span><span class='line'>source $HOME<span class="sr">/.vim/</span>vimrc/plugins.<span class="k">vim</span>
</span><span class='line'>source $HOME<span class="sr">/.vim/</span>vimrc/settings.<span class="k">vim</span>
</span><span class='line'>source $HOME<span class="sr">/.vim/</span>vimrc/spelling.<span class="k">vim</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">&quot; Source a local vimrc if it exists</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">if</span> filereadable<span class="p">(</span>expand<span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;$HOME/.vimrc.local&quot;</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>  source $HOME/.vimrc.local
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">endif</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now each of my files are much smaller and easier to manage! It’s also quite
simple to navigate to each of these files. I’ve set up <leader>; to open up
a tab with the .vimrc, and then I can use vim’s handy gf action to open up the
file given by the filename under the cursor. I’ve included a nice way to allow
for local .vimrc additions as well.</p>

<p>If you’re interested, check out my vimfiles on github here:
<a href="https://github.com/thenovices/dotfiles">https://github.com/thenovices/dotfiles</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[List Lunacy: Problem and Solution]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2011/10/30/list-lunacy-problem-and-solution/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-30T17:53:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2011/10/30/list-lunacy-problem-and-solution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I came across this interesting problem a few weeks ago, and I had a lot of fun
thinking about it and solving it. In this post, I&rsquo;ll cover:</p>

<ol>
<li>The problem statement</li>
<li>Approaching the problem and coming to a solution</li>
<li>Experimentally verifying the solution with an implementation</li>
<li>A proof of the solution for theoretical verification</li>
<li>Interesting things I found looking around after solving the problem</li>
</ol>


<h2>The Problem Statement</h2>

<p>Write a function that returns a random node from a linked list of unknown
length in <strong>O(1) space</strong> and <strong>O(n) time</strong>. (Finding a solution in O(1) time is
not only algorithmically interesting, but is also realistic if the linked list
is too large to fit in memory). You may only traverse through the linked list
<strong>once</strong> (i.e. you can&rsquo;t traverse it once to get the length of the list, then
again to pick a node).</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Approach</h2>

<p>The key thing to think about while approaching this problem is that the
algorithm has to be ready to terminate at any moment because you don&rsquo;t know
when the list is going to end. The first thing that this tells you is that the
function should always be holding onto a node that it will return if the list
comes to an end. This implies that the function should pick up the first node
that it comes to, and then with every node it traverses, it should replace the
node it is holding with some probability. The probability of replacing the node
that it&rsquo;s holding with the one it&rsquo;s traversing should be decreasing with the
number of nodes seen because as the list gets longer, the probability of
picking up a node gets smaller. The probability also depends on the number of
nodes that have been traversed, but it&rsquo;s not yet clear what the function is.
(Think about why the probability can&rsquo;t depend on something like the number of
times the function replaced the node it&rsquo;s holding or the number of nodes it has
seen since the last replacement).</p>

<p>The second thing to realize will yield the solution to the problem, although
initially it may not be obvious why it works. If we think about the fact that
the algorithm has to be ready at any moment to terminate because it might reach
the end of the list at any moment, then we realize that the algorithm always
has to pick up the <em>k</em>th node with probabiliy <em>1/k</em>. It&rsquo;s clear that if the
algorithm uses this method, then once the list ends, the algorithm would have
picked the very last node in the list with the correct probability. If the
length of the list were <em>n</em>, then the algorithm would pick up the last node in
the list with probability <em>1/n</em>. But because the algorithm has to treat every
single node as if it were going to be last node in the list, then it has to do
this for all the nodes in the list!</p>

<p>This seems unintuitive because it isn&rsquo;t clear why all the other nodes also get
returned with the same probability, but at the same time the reasoning appears
to be correct in an odd, nonconstructivist way. Let&rsquo;s write a quick
implementation of this function to get some initial verification that it is
correct, and then afterward we&rsquo;ll do a more rigorous analysis and proof so that
we can see why this solution is correct. Fortunately in this case it doesn&rsquo;t
take very long to write an implementation (at least in a high-level language
like Ruby), so we can do that before proving the correctness of the solution.
It&rsquo;ll be fun, and if we&rsquo;re wrong, the output may give some clues to the correct
solution. But in other cases, it may be more effective to prove that the
solution is correct before diving into an implementation, because then if your
code gives you the wrong answer, you can&rsquo;t be entirely sure that it&rsquo;s your
solution and not your code that is the problem.</p>

<h2>An Implementation</h2>

<p>I chose to write a quick implementation in Ruby because it&rsquo;d be fast to write
up (and also because it&rsquo;s currently my favorite language). I used an array
instead of a real linked list not only because it doesn&rsquo;t change the core of
the algorithm and it saves time, but also because it improves clarity and
avoids possible bugs in dealing with linked lists.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>list_lunacy.rb </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">get_random_node</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">arr</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">node</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kp">nil</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">arr</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">each_with_index</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">el</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">i</span><span class="o">|</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="nb">rand</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="mi">0</span> <span class="c1"># returns true with probability 1/i</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">node</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">el</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">node</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">.</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">to_a</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">count</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">a</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">size</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">1_000_000</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">times</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">count</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="n">get_random_node</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">p</span> <span class="n">count</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>./list_lunacy.rb
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">[</span>100061, 100070, 100450, 99472, 99986, 99762, 100038, 99957, 100092, 100112<span class="o">]</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This data yields a mean of 100,000 and a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_error">standard
error</a> of 0.2519,
which gives us a good deal of confidence about the correctness of our solution.
Hurray!</p>

<h2>A Proof (no, actually two!)</h2>

<p>So now that we have a good experimental verification that our solution is
correct, let&rsquo;s return back and think about why it is that our solution works.
In particular, it isn&rsquo;t yet clear why our method of holding onto a node at all
time and replacing it with the <em>k</em>th node with probability <em>1/k</em> results in all
the nodes being picked with equal probability. Let&rsquo;s take a look.I&rsquo;ll go
through two different proofs with two different approaches: one that
immediately proves our solution correct for lists of arbitrary length, and
another that proceeds using proof by induction.</p>

<h3>Proof 1: For lists of length <em>n</em></h3>

<p>Suppose that we have a linked of length <em>n</em>. For the <em>k</em>th node in the linked
list, where <em>k = 1, 2,&hellip;,n</em>, we pick it with probability <em>1/k</em> and we hold
onto our previously picked node with probability <em>(k-1)/k</em>. In order for the
<em>k</em>th node to be picked and held onto until the very end to be returned, the
algorithm must pick node <em>k</em>, and then cannot pick any of the successive nodes.
It doesn&rsquo;t matter what the algorithm does for nodes <em>1</em> through <em>k-1</em> because
all that matters is the last node that is picked by the algorithm.</p>

<p>And so, the probability that the <em>k</em>th node is picked and returned by the
algorithm is simply the product of the probability of the <em>k</em>th node being
picked and the probabilities that all of the successive nodes are not picked,
which turns out to be:</p>

<p><img src="http://brandonkliu.com/public/images/list_lunacy.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Since this is true for all <em>k</em>, we see that our algorithm indeed does return a
random node with equal probability. The <em>k</em>th node initially may be picked with
probability <em>1/k</em>, but with every additional node that is traversed, the
probability that it is still held onto &ldquo;erodes&rdquo; down to <em>1/n</em>.</p>

<h3>Proof 2: A proof by induction</h3>

<p>We proceed using proof by induction on the length of the linked list.</p>

<p><strong>Basis</strong>: The linked list has length 1.</p>

<p>In the case of length 1, our algorithm immediately picks up the first node
(with probability 1), and because the linked list ends there, it returns that
node with probability 1, as desired.</p>

<p><strong>Induction Step</strong>: Assume our inductive hypothesis true for all linked lists
of length at most <em>k</em>, where <em>k</em> is greater than 1, and show that our inductive
hypothesis holds for a linked list of length <em>k+1</em>.</p>

<p>Suppose that we have a linked list of length <em>k+1</em>. By the time the algorithm
has traversed the first <em>k</em> nodes in the linked list, the node it is currently
holding onto could be any of the first <em>k</em> nodes, each with probability <em>1/k</em>,
by our inductive hypothesis. When the algorithm reaches node <em>k+1</em>, it could
pick the last node with probability <em>1/(k+1)</em>, or it may hold onto the previous
node with probability <em>k/(k+1)</em>, which means that if the algorithm held onto
the previous node, it would be holding onto any one of the first <em>k</em> nodes,
each with probability <em>(1/k) * (k/(k+1)) = 1/(k+1)</em>. Hence, when the algorithm
returns, it will return any of the <em>k+1</em> nodes, each with probability
<em>1/(k+1)</em>. This completes the induction step.</p>

<h2>Additional interesting information</h2>

<p>While writing this blog post, I was googling around, curious to see whether
anyone else had writting on this problem. I ended up discovering that this
problem is actually a special case of the Reservoir sampling problem, which can
be described as follows: Suppose that you have a incoming stream of pieces of
data. You can only see each piece of data once and you don&rsquo;t know how much
total data is coming through. You need to return <em>k</em> pieces of data from this
stream, <strong>evenly distributed</strong> from the original stream.</p>

<p>Sounds similar, right? The algorithm for the reservoir sampling problem turns
out to be quite similar to the one we&rsquo;ve come up here. If you&rsquo;re interested,
you can read a little bit more on
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reservoir_sampling">Wikipedia</a> or the <a href="http://xlinux.nist.gov/dads//HTML/reservoirSampling.html">Dictionary
of Algorithms and Data
Structures</a>, although
there&rsquo;s not too much information there. But there&rsquo;s a very interesting post on
this reservoir sampling problem and interesting extensions, such as the
weighted reservoir sampling problem and the distributed reservoir sampling
problem here: <a href="http://gregable.com/2007/10/reservoir-sampling.html.">http://gregable.com/2007/10/reservoir-sampling.html.</a> All very
interesting things to think about.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Education for a Successful Entrepreneur]]></title>
    <link href="http://branliu.com/blog/2011/10/23/the-education-for-a-successful-entrepreneur/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-23T17:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://branliu.com/blog/2011/10/23/the-education-for-a-successful-entrepreneur</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spend a lot of time thinking about how I can make the best use of my time,
given my circumstances and where I am in life, and one of the most important
things that I&rsquo;ve had to think about is the division of time between school and
entrepreneurship. Given that I&rsquo;m passionate about entrepreneurship and deeply
involved on campus, it would make sense for me to be spending much of my free
time working on projects, generating ideas, and practicing entrepreneurship.
After all, school is a wonderful time to work on a startup, because you don&rsquo;t
need to be making a salary, you have so many talented and ambitious peers, and
in the worst case of your startup failing, you can always fall back to your
schoolwork.</p>

<p>But this semester, I&rsquo;ve made a deliberate effort to cut down on my projects and
entrepreneurial activities in order to focus on schoolwork. I&rsquo;ve thought a lot
and there are many reasons why I&rsquo;ve made this decision to focus more on
schoolwork, and one of those reasons is that I believe entrepreneurship is
nothing more than a means to an end, and not an end in itself, as many think.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>What is entrepreneurship? I love the practice of starting off these
definitional discussions with a Wikipedia quote.</p>

<blockquote><p>Entrepreneurship is the act of being an entrepreneur, which can be defined as<br/>&#8220;one who undertakes innovations, finance and business acumen in an effort to<br/>transform innovations into economic goods&#8221;.</p></blockquote>


<p>Although not everyone may agree with this precise definition, at least it
serves to lend some concreteness to this notion of entrepreneurship that we are
discussing. But anyway, a precise definition is not necessary for what I want
to explore here.</p>

<p>So, given this definition, what does an entrepreneur need to know in order to
be successful? Yes, as according to Wikipedia&rsquo;s definition, business and
financial acumen are indeed needed. This is where many people see
entrepreneurship start and end: the business skills of building a product,
positioning yourself to a market, and growing a company as well as the
financial skills of raising money, managing capital, and turning profits. These
are all indeed the skills required of any competent entrepreneur, but I believe
that they are not the ones that lie at the heart of entrepreneurship. Just as
Disney may be incredible at designing amusement parks, creating animations, and
composing music, all those skills are secondary to what lies at the heart of
what Disney does and why it is so successful: making people happy by delivering
a magical experience.</p>

<p>If you are without a deep understanding the core of what you want to do and how
to do it, all the peripheral skills fall to the wayside and become meaningless.
And so I believe that becoming a successful entrepreneur isn&rsquo;t just about
attending workshops on raising your seed round of funding or mastering the art
of the pitch. The heart of entrepreneurship lies in innovation, in discovering
and understanding a problem that is deeply important to people to society. It
lies in having the foresight and vision to see the world differently and in
having the domain skills and expertise to forge the road ahead to create the
future you see. Every entrepreneur is passionate about a different problem and
has deep expertise in what they&rsquo;re working on, which is why there is no
entrepreneurial class or conference or forum out there that can tell you what
sort of innovation you should be working on and how you&rsquo;ll succeed. Only you
can find that on your own.</p>

<p>But that is what an education is for. You dive deep into a domain so that
you&rsquo;re prepared to be a leader in your field and to see what it&rsquo;s like to be at
the edge of human knowledge. You study history (not necessarily the history of
civilizations, but perhaps the history of other things, like technology) and
learn about the past so that you may better see into the future, because you
discover that history repeats itself. You study a breadth of subjects to know
more about the world we live in and you learn from the innovations in every
field because oftentimes the best innovations come from somewhere outside your
domain. You challenge yourself by studying hard theoretical subjects like math
or philosophy not for their applications, but because the intellectual rigor
will train your mind to be learn quickly, process rapidly, and see a bit
further into the future by understanding the implications of all that you are
exposed to.</p>

<p>This is why an education is important, especially for those who wish to be
successful in entrepreneurship and create something truly innovative &ndash;
something that requires foresight, knowledge, and lots of hard work. The other
skills have their place and their time to be learned, but you must focus on
what is important first. Successful entrepreneurs aren&rsquo;t lucky; they know
exactly what they are doing and they&rsquo;ve prepared for it, which is why they
succeed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
